"Is Ozempic (Semaglutide) Safe?"
GLP-1 weight-loss drugs.
How safe are they?
Regulatory authorities
have expressed concerns
about the potential risk
of acute pancreatitis,
thyroid cancer,
and kidney failure,
warnings that are
appropriately conveyed
in every box of drugs
handed to a patient.
Here’s the actual package insert
for high-dose Ozempic,
sold for weight loss as Wegovy.
Warnings and precautions
include thyroid tumors,
acute inflammation
of the pancreas,
acute gallbladder disease,
heightened risk
of low blood sugars
if you’re on blood
sugar-lowering medications,
acute kidney injury,
allergic reactions,
worsening eye disease
for those with type 2 diabetes,
an increase in heart rate
that should be monitored,
and suicidal thoughts
and behaviors.
And the package insert
for the other major
GLP-1 weight loss drug,
tirzepatide, sold as Zepbound,
reads almost word for word
the same.
Let’s start with the good news,
suicide.
The possibility of an adverse
psychiatric event on GLP-1 drugs
is biologically plausible
because GLP-1 receptors
are widely expressed
in the central nervous system,
including our brain.
So, what does the science show?
This meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
did not highlight
any detrimental effect
on these drugs on mental health,
including suicide.
Now, this meta-analysis
only covered studies
up through the end of 2023
and only clinical trials,
and those with mental illnesses
are usually excluded
from such studies.
But there have been
newer studies done
with subjects
out in the real world,
and again,
no clear increased risk.
And this study,
on the association
of the Ozempic drug semaglutide
with risk of suicidal ideation
in another cohort
found that the drug
was associated
with a lower risk
for incident and recurrent
suicidal ideation,
apparently cutting
suicidal thoughts
by more than half,
compared to those
on the older, less effective
weight-loss drugs.
After all,
a weight-reducing treatment
that limits
the burden of obesity
could improve mood.
I told you suicide
was the good news!
Now, on to cancer.
Both Wegovy, high-dose Ozempic,
and Zepbound (tirzepatide),
carry so-called
black box warnings
for thyroid cancer risk.
Black box warnings
are the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration’s
strictest caution
about potentially
life-threatening hazards.
In rodents, these drugs
cause dose-dependent
and duration-dependent
thyroid tumors
at clinically relevant
exposures,
meaning the kind of doses
prescribed to humans.
Now, we don’t know yet
whether these drugs cause
a thyroid cancer called
medullary thyroid carcinoma,
which is a cancer of
the thyroid C cells in humans.
To be on the safe side,
the drugs shouldn’t
be prescribed
for high-risk individuals,
like those with a personal
or family history
of thyroid cancer,
but it’s not like the rats
had thyroid cancer
running in their families.
Doctors should counsel
their patients
to remain alert
for symptoms of thyroid tumors,
like a lump
or swelling in the neck,
trouble swallowing,
shortness of breath,
or persistent hoarseness.
I’d be curious in the comments
to see if any viewers
who’ve been prescribed
these drugs
were told any of this
by their prescribing physicians.
Can’t we just ultrasound
people’s necks
to see if they develop
thyroid tumors on these drugs?
That’s considered to be
of uncertain value,
since no such studies
have been done.
Now, there have been
studies done
on GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
and the risk of thyroid cancer
in people.
This was the first major one
raising concern,
published in 2023.
Researchers found increased risk
of all thyroid cancers
and specifically,
medullary thyroid cancer
in people using these drugs,
particularly after taking them
for a few years.
A commentary
citing the study asked,
"Is it the time
to be concerned?"
Maybe that one study
was just a fluke?
No, after putting together
all the best studies,
a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
found, again,
a significant increase
in the risk
of overall thyroid cancer,
about 52 percent greater odds.
That sounds bad,
until you realize
just how rare
the cancer is overall.
The incidence of thyroid cancer
in this kind of population
is 0.285 cases
per 1,000 patient years.
This means that
over a span of 10 years,
we’d only expect
about three people out of 1,000
to get that cancer.
So, even if you bump up
that risk by 50 percent,
you’re still only talking
about four in 1,000
getting it over a decade,
compared to three in 1,000
if you hadn’t started
taking the drugs.
That translates to a five-year
"number needed to harm"
of 1,349.
That means that even if this
were truly cause-and-effect,
it would take treating
1,349 people for five years
to cause a single additional
case of thyroid cancer.
And even if you’re
the unlucky soul who gets it,
it’s pretty mild, as cancers go.
The five-year
relative survival rate,
meaning the likelihood
you’ll still be alive
five years after diagnosis
compared to people
without the cancer
is 98.4 percent.
Okay, but what about the risk
of pancreatic cancer
with the use of these drugs?
That has a relative
five-year survival rate
of only 12.8 percent.
You can see the difference
between the incidence rates
and the death rates.
For thyroid cancer,
a bunch of people are
diagnosed with it,
but very few die from it,
whereas for pancreatic cancer,
almost everyone who gets it
dies from it.
So, do these drugs cause
pancreatic cancer?
That’s exactly the question
I’ll address next.